Xiang Yuansheng!
向远生
Are you okay?
你没事吧
I'm fine.
我没事
I'll call the others.
我去喊二白他们
Be careful,
你小心点
Captain! Are you in there?
队长 你们在屋里吗
Who locked the door?
谁给门锁了
Step aside.
让一下骆警官
I'm not an ordinary foreigner.
我不是普通的侨民
You have no right to arrest me.
你们没有权力逮捕我
A soldier?
你是军人
Yes,
是的
I am a soldier of the Empire of Japan.
我是大日本帝国的军人
Japanese Special Marine Corps in Shanghai?
海军上海特别陆战队
Sure enough.
果然
When our people arrive,
一会儿等骆珉敏
we'll bring him
他们过来
back to the Fourth Station.
我们把人带回四所
What are you doing?
你干什么
We can't handle this case.
四所处理不了你的案子
I'll take you to Shiliupu.
我把你带到十六铺分局
What?
你要把人
Shiliupu?
交给十六铺分局
Yes. I should do this.
这本来就是分局的案子
Tell me!
你看着我回答
Will you bring him to Feng Guangyun?
你要把人交给冯广云
I'm suspended,
我现在是停职
not dismissed.
不是被撤职
I still have a chance to be a cop.
我还有机会做警察
Chen Hao,
陈浩
do you know what you're doing?
你知道自己在干什么吗
Erbai will open it for you.
二白他们会帮你打开的
Go!
走
Chen Hao!
陈浩
Do you work for Feng?
你是冯广云的人
You know what I mean.
你明白我的意思
This is not
这不是
the way to Shiliupu.
去十六铺分局的路
Why?
你想做什么
For Luo Minmin,
骆珉敏的账
I've not gotten even with you.
我还没找你算呢
Shut the fuck up!
你给老子闭嘴
Go!
走
Captain Chen, nice to meet you again.
陈队长 我们又见面了
What do you want?
你想干吗
He is suspected
他被怀疑涉嫌一起
of a criminal case
发生在法租界内的
in the French Concession.
刑事案件
This is the arrest warrant.
这是逮捕令
I study
我是
in the Japanese Youth
日本青年实业学校的
Industrial School.
学生
I've never been to there.
我没去过法租界
On the 26th last month,
上个月二十六号
you stabbed
你在望云路公寓
a middle-aged man with a dagger
袭击了一名中年男子
at an apartment on Wangyun Road.
作案工具就是一把匕首
There are no more than
就是这把防身格斗匕首
100 daggers of this type in total,
生产总共不超过一百把
and each batch is different.
而且每一批都有区别
It's easy to trace the source.
所以很容易找到源头
In February this year,
今年二月份
a British inspector
一名英籍探长
was killed on
在法租界的福开森路
Folkson Road.
被害
After this,
他出事过后
the dagger that he had with him
他随身携带的匕首
disappeared.
就消失不见了
By coincidence,
很不巧
it's the one lost.
就是这一把
We have reason
所以我们有理由怀疑
to believe that
你在法租界
you're the murderer.
谋杀了一名英国人
Captain Chen,
陈队长
can you hand him over to us now?
可以把人交给我们了吗
I'm the one who caught him.
你这是在抢人
You're in the French Concession,
这是在法租界
you must follow the rules.
也是规矩
Let's go.
收队
What happened?
发生什么了
Where's Captain Chen?
队长呢
Where's the Japanese?
日本人呢
Chen Hao took him away.
陈浩把人带走了
Who handcuffed you here?
谁把你铐在这儿的
We're also locked
我们刚才也被人
in the corridor just now.
锁在走廊里了
I don't know which jerk did this.
不知道哪个小赤佬干的
Who handcuffed you here?
是谁把你铐在这儿的
Chen Hao has already handed the man over.
陈浩已经把人交出去了
What?
交出去
To whom?
交给谁啊
It's all over.
事情结束了
Let's go.
都回去吧
Takagi Tamaki has been
高木环已经被带回去了
imprisoned in the Central Police Station.
现在关在中央捕房
That day, you said
那天你说
it's almost impossible to give him a sentence.
判刑几乎是不可能了
Is it still working even with
就算有匕首这种铁证
the ironclad evidence?
也不可能吗
There is no
日本在上海
Japanese concession
在法律上
legally in Shanghai.
没有真正意义上的租界
But there are
但是他们在虹口
Japanese military power
有军事力量
in Hongkou,
在公董局
full-time directors
有日侨专职董事
in the Council,
在巡捕房
and
他们有上至
patrol policemen and officers
三粒星东洋大班
at various levels
下至东洋三道头的
in the police station.
日侨巡捕
In recent years,
这几年
Japan has greatly
他们的势力已经
increased their penetration.
越来越不一样了
The Japanese against the law
那些犯了法的日侨
will only be
只会被移交到
handed over to the consulate.
日本领事馆
No one
英美法巡捕
has the right to interpose at all.
根本无权干涉
But then,
那移交之后
athletes will be dealt with
他们就是自己的裁判
by their own referees.
处理自己的运动员
That's right.
对
Fines are the most.
大多只是罚钱了事
But some will be
但是还是有一部分
extradited back
会因为工部局
because of
和公董局的指控
the charges of councils.
被引渡回日本
If arrested
那如果
by the police of the
像是被国民政府的
National Government,
警察逮捕
a quiet release
最后换来的
would be done by Tan Shiyuan
就是谭施远的暗箱操作
through black case work.
悄无声息地给放了
I'm eager
我恨不得
to see an immediate execution
马上判他们死刑
by shooting.
把他们枪毙
But I know it's impossible.
但我知道这不可能
Extradition back to Japan
先让他们回日本苟活着
is at least
至少
equivalent to being driven out of Shanghai.
也算把他们赶出了上海
Xiang Yuansheng
其实这件事情
actually paid the most for this.
向远生是付出最多的人
But it's not
但是现在
the time to tell him the truth.
我可能不能告诉他
If he knew that
如果向远生知道
Tan Shiyuan was involved,
谭施远有问题
he'd take advantages of his identity
他会利用自己的条件
to investigate Tan.
去调查他
This will bring too many new twists
这会带来太多变数
against us to save people.
不利于我们救人
His identity?
利用他的条件
Right.
对
Chen Hao,
陈浩
you may
你可能不知道
not know this.
向远生的身份
I know it.
我知道
Our leader
组长是在
was arrested at the home
军政部次长家里
of the Undersecretary Hua.
被捕的
Although he didn't say anything,
虽然向远生没有说过
I can guess that
但我能猜到
he is
他应该就是
the son of Mr. Hua.
军政部次长的儿子
Ms. Shi,
石小姐
I've been troubled by a question.
我一直想问一个问题
Is he
向远生会是
our comrade but just
我们的同志吗
not connected
只是暂时
to us yet?
没跟我们连上线
Just like I did before.
就跟我之前一样
When he came to the Fourth Station,
他刚来四所的时候
his certificate was given
手里面拿着的证件
to the leader by me in person.
是我亲手交给组长的
I was thinking of this at that time.
我当时就在想这个问题
But apart from
但是他除了是
what's mentioned,
军政部次长儿子
he's also a student
这一身份以外
of the elite class
他还是蒋介石
of the naval school
嫡系海军学校的学生
in direct line with Chiang Kai-shek.
精英班的预备学员
After graduation,
毕业之后
he may be the backbone of the New Navy
他可能就是国民政府
of the National Government.
新海军的中坚力量
He used to
在这之前
live in Yihe Road,
他一直生活在颐和路
and studied
而且
in an army school for 2 years.
在陆军学校读过两年
His track of development
他的成长轨迹
is different from most people.
和大部分的人们都不同
My answer
所以如果
to your question
你要问我答案
is that it's impossible,
我的答案是不可能
even
未来
in the future.
也很难
I always thought
之前我一直以为
that he's
他留在上海
just wasting a month
查孟家凶杀案
investigating
耽误的只是
the murder case in Shanghai.
一个月的时间
Surprisingly,
结果他却赌上了
he traded his future for it.
自己的前程
Although he is on the
向远生虽然和我们
different road from us,
是两条路上的人
our goal
但是我们的目标
is the same.
是相同的
To better protect the organization,
只是出于对组织的保护
we could neither tell him
我们既不能告诉他
nor get him involved in.
也不能让他参与其中
I understand.
我明白
Out of protection
不管是出于
for the organization
对组织的保护
and him,
还是他自己
I won't
都不能让他
reveal anything about Tan Shiyuan,
卷进谭施远的事
but keep him as far away as possible.
我会让他离得越远越好
However...
只不过
I've already
我已经把他
considered him as my best friend.
当作生死之交了
Why don't you go in?
怎么不进去啊
I planned to hand him over to Shiliupu.
本来想把人交到分局
But he's taken away
可刚到法租界
by the Council
公董局的人
in the French Concession.
就把人带走了
Then...
他们在法租界
Why not to the Fourth Station?
为什么不把人带回四所
You are afraid that he'll
你怕他在你的手上
be taken away from you?
被抓住
Yes.
对
I've told you.
我说过
I don't want to be dismissed.
我不想停职变撤职
I wanna continue being a policeman.
我还想继续做警察
So, you're clear that
这说明你心里很清楚
Feng Guangyun will protect the killer.
冯广云在袒护凶手
I don't believe
我不相信
you still planned to
你明知道这一点
hand over the man to him.
还会把人交给冯广云
Do you really think
你真以为我是个
I'll never compromise?
永不妥协的人
Even if he's not trustworthy,
冯广云有问题
there are many
也只是一个冯广云
higher-ups
分局上面
in Shanghai Public Security Bureau.
还有上海市公安局
If you don't trust
还有副局长局长
the police system
如果你信不过
of the National Government,
国民政府的警察系统
why do you
你为什么还要
insist on being a policeman?
继续当警察
Those two Japanese
那两个日本人
will be charged with murder.
会被控告谋杀
The best result
最好的结果
is to extradite them back.
就是把他们引渡回日本
Is it the best?
这就是最好的结果
Yes, it is.
对 这就是最好的结果
I tried my best.
我只能努力到这儿了
After such a long investigation,
我们查了这么久
we only have one final step left!
现在已经走到最后一步
One more!
最后一步就差一步
Why didn't you
你要妥协
compromise earlier
为什么不早点妥协
but wait until now?
非要等到现在
Do you want all our efforts
让我们所有人的努力
to be in vain?
都白费
I'm easy to act on impulse.
我是容易头脑发热
But I'm not stupid!
但我不是傻子
I know what I'm supposed to do!
我清楚我自己该干什么
Have you ever thought of Li Qiushi?
你有想过黎秋实吗
She's only 8.
她才八岁
She saw her parents killed
她亲眼看见自己的父母
being killed with her own eyes.
死在那个人的手里
More than this.
还有骆珉敏
To catch the murderer,
她为了抓住凶手
Luo Minmin was almost
差点被打死
beaten to death.
她都不肯松手
Have you ever thought of them?
你想过她们俩吗
And
还有
the dead pawnshop worker
已经死了的当铺伙计
and the parlor owner.
和麻将馆老板
The result should not be like this.
这个结果对不起所有人
We've been working for a long time.
我以为我们合作到现在
I thought you'd discuss with me beforehand.
起码你会提前跟我商量
You're a cop just for fun.
你做警察只是玩玩而已
It's not what you wanna do most.
这不是你最想干的事情
If you're tired in Shanghai,
上海待不下去了
you can go back to Nanjing.
你可以回南京
But I'm not like you.
可我跟你不一样
It's related to my future.
这是我的前途
I can't make fun of it!
我不能拿我前途开玩笑
I don't need to discuss with anyone.
我不需要跟任何人商量
Never mention this
从今以后
again from now on!
我都不想提这件事
I hope you have reasons
我希望你是有原因
that you cannot express,
没有说出口
and I won't ask too much about them.
既然你不说我也不会问
But you're just talking nonsense.
但你刚才说的那些鬼话
I don't believe a single word.
我是不可能相信的
Qiu Shi can't wait
秋实已经等不及
to see you.
要见你了
I've already bought her
我已经帮她买好
a ticket to Hong Kong.
去香港的船票
There are trusted friends
那边有孟先生和孟太太
of her parents.
信得过的朋友
All well arranged.
现在一切安排妥当
When to leave?
什么时候出发
2 days later.
两天之后
Those two Japanese
另外关于那两个日本人
haven been confirmed
警务处已经查清了
as members of
他们是海军
Japanese Special Marine Corps in Shanghai.
上海特别陆战队的人
Qiushi's parents
秋实父母
are important taxpayers.
是法租界的重要纳税人
They're murdered.
公董局知道他们遇害
It made the Council furious.
也感到愤怒
The Council's interests
毕竟这也伤害了
were also damaged after all.
他们的利益
Besides,
再加上
other businessmen with properties
在法租界有产业的
in the French Concession
其他商人
also asked the Council
也开始向公董局施压
to protect taxpayers.
要求保护纳税人
So the Council
所以现在公董局
formally demanded that
开始和日本领事馆
the Japanese consulate
提出交涉
severely punish the killer
一是要求严惩凶手
and
二是要求
not interfere with the taxpayers' assets.
不得干涉纳税人的资产
I know you fought for it
我知道这是你在公董局
from the Council.
争取到的结果
Thank you very much.
谢谢
I should be the one to say thanks.
应该是我说谢谢才是
Mr. And Mrs. Meng
孟先生和孟太太
are my good friends.
是我的朋友
I appreciate
我很感激
what you've done for them.
你为他们做的一切
The killer wouldn't have been
要不是因为你
caught so fast without you.
凶手不会那么快落网
Is sentencing
他们真的不可能
impossible?
被判刑吗
In past cases,
从以往的案例来看
extradition is the best possible result.
引渡已经是最好的结果
Only a piece of paper?
怎么就只有一张纸
Dedicate everything
苟利社稷
to the country construction.
死生以之
What does
远生哥哥
that mean?
这句话是什么意思啊
If something
如果一件事情
is good for the country,
对国家有利
do it even if
个人或生或死
it costs your life.
都会去做的
You know Mr. He of the
军政部的何部长
Ministry of Military Affairs?
您知道吧
His driver
我和他的司机啊
is my old friend.
是老相识
Thanks to him,
托他的福啊
ladies from official families
经常有官员的太太小姐
often come to my shop.
到我这儿来做东西
Amazing.
那您这店
You'd have many
岂不是经常有
of the Ministry visiting here, innit?
军政部的大人物光顾
Honestly,
不谦虚地说
in the decades since opening the store,
我在南京开店几十年
I've been
每个月
gonna Shanghai twice a month.
沪宁之间总要跑上两趟
I can get
上海有的
everything new there into my store
我这里不出半个月
within half a month.
也能有
So
所以
the rich people in Nanjing
南京城里的豪门贵人
often come to my shop.
他都是我的客人
To be honest,
不瞒您说 老板
I come here
其实我
to find a belt
就是想搞一条
just like
跟这个皮带
this one.
一模一样的皮带
Look.
您看啊
There's "Shunchang",
我发现这后面
the same name
有顺昌二字
as your store.
和您的店名相符啊
Isn't this
是不是您的手艺
If I
不过如果
recall correctly,
我不记错的话
this belt was made
这条皮带应该是
for Mrs. Hua
是华夫人
for her second son.
为她二公子定做的
Mrs. Hua?
华夫人
You mean the wife
莫非是军政部次长
of the Undersecretary Hua?
华次长的太太
Yes.
是啊
But,
不是
how...
这个
did you get it?
怎么在你这儿
By chance!
机缘巧合
What a coincidence!
机缘巧合呀
Measure me, please.
老板 给我量量尺寸
Captain Wei.
魏队长
Sorry to keep you.
久等了
Never mind.
没关系
What did the Secretary-General say?
秘书长他怎么说
Did he allow me to arrest Hua Zhen?
他允许我逮捕华桢吗
He asked
秘书长问
do you have any other evidence?
还有没有其他的证据
No.
没有
But this belt is
但这条皮带
a direct proof that Hua Zhen
已经完全可以直接证明
has a connection with the Communist Party.
华桢跟共产党有来往
Our team
侦查队现在
have reason to arrest him.
有理由逮捕华桢的
Please tell the Secretary that
你告诉郭秘书长一声
it's only been a short time
就说我逮捕张润金
since I arrested Zhang Runjin.
到现在时间很短
Hua Zhen may not
华桢很有可能
even know that
完全没有发现
I've obtained such evidence.
我掌握了他的证据
It's the best time to arrest him!
现在逮捕他是最佳时机
Have you found
邓铭远跟华桢之间
any other relationships
除了是师生关系之外
between them
你还有没有查到
besides
他们之间
Deng Mingyuan being his teacher?
有没有其他的关系
Not yet.
那倒没有
Deng
邓铭远现在
is no longer useful.
已经没有利用价值了
As long as
只要郭秘书长
I'm allowed me to arrest Hua Zhen,
允许我逮捕华桢
I can get
我能从他身上
anything I want from him.
审到我任何想要的证据
Captain Wei,
魏队长
Deng
明天啊
will be escorted to Nanjing tomorrow.
邓铭远就押解来南京了
He can only stay
他只能在你们
in your area
淞沪警备司令部
for one last day.
留这么最后一天
If you can not
要是您还不能抓住机会
seize the opportunity
再得到什么
to find more,
其他证据的话
I'm afraid the Secretary
恐怕秘书长
will not grant your request.
不会同意您逮捕华桢的
The belt...
皮带
it enough?
不够是吗
The Secretary
秘书长办事
has always called for solid evidence.
一向要求稳妥
By the way,
对了魏队
don't come here
下次就不要
next time.
直接来这儿了
After all, we're in the capital,
毕竟这是在首都
and it's easy for people
咱们这样的见面
to think we're interfering
容易让别人引起误会
with the investigation.
是在干扰调查
You're right.
对对对
I'm sorry.
是是是
I didn't think it through.
是属下考虑不周 抱歉
You might leave now.
那就不送了
Captain.
队长
Where's Hua Zhen now?
查到华桢搬哪去了吗
In Jinmen Hotel.
查到了 金门饭店
How about Deng Mingyuan?
邓铭远那边什么情况
All handover procedures
南京来的人
have been completed.
已经办完全部交接手续
The departure is 1 hour later.
再有一个小时就出发
You hurry back
高平顺你赶快回去
and update the chief
向参谋长汇报我们
on our progress in Nanjing.
在南京的最新进展
Make sure
务必给我
to buy me another hour.
再争取一个小时
Got it!
知道了
I have to interrogate Deng again.
我得再审一遍邓铭远
Sorry, Sir.
抱歉先生
The guest had made it clear that
房间客人特意交代过
he wouldn't see anyone.
他不会客
I have an emergency.
我有急事
As a rule,
饭店有规定
we can't tell you
我们确实不能
his room number.
告诉您房间号
I'm Wei Daiqing
我是为政府工作的
from Shanghai Garrison Command.
淞沪警备司令部魏岱擎
May I see your
方便出示一下
identification, please?
您的证件吗
Thanks.
谢谢
Sit down please,
华先生坐
Mr. Hua.
坐
I don't seem to
我不记得跟魏队长
have seen you before.
打过交道
What can I do for you?
找我有什么事儿吗
This is not
华先生
the first time we've met.
我们俩见过
I met you
那天在南京
at your father's
你家
birthday party
那天正好是
in Nanjing.
华次长的寿宴
But I was on a mission then.
不过我是去执行任务的
And I arrested Deng Mingyuan.
逮捕的邓铭远
He's now
邓铭远呢
prisoned in
现在关押在
the Shanghai Garrison Command.
淞沪警备司令部
I know that
我知道啊
you've always
你出于个人的原因
looked up to him
一直很敬重他
because he's your teacher.
他毕竟教过你嘛
We're in opposition with him,
虽然我们跟他立场不同
but after all,
但到了这一步
one can not be too ruthless.
人也不能太过无情
I can understand
那点尊师重道
how much you respect him.
我还是可以理解的
If
如果
see him for the last time,
你想见他最后一面
I can arrange it.
我可以安排
And
当然了
if you wanna avoid suspicion,
如果你想避嫌的话
then just pretend I haven't come.
那就当魏某人白跑一趟
The last time?
最后一面
What does that mean?
是什么意思
1 hour later,
一个小时之后
Deng will be taken to Nanjing.
邓铭远即将押解南京
And once he arrives,
到了南京
he'll be shot.
即刻执行枪决
Mr. Deng.
老师
Hua Zhen.
华桢
Mr. Deng,
邓组长
I have nothing more to ask you.
我没有什么要问你的了
Out of my kindness,
出于同情心
I've made
我特地
a special request
从参谋长那儿
to the chief
申请了这次提审
for your student
把您的学生
to see you here.
华先生给请来了
You can write down anything
有什么需要交代的
you want to say.
需要记下来的
By the rules,
按规定
the condemned person is allowed
死刑犯在临终的时候
for a family meeting before execution.
有权见亲人一面
But as far as I know,
可据我查
you don't have
你在南京
any relatives in Nanjing.
没有任何的亲人
And no one would
而且也不会有任何人
go to the prison for you.
去中央陆军监狱去看你
So whether you two
无论你们俩关系
are on good terms or not,
亲近也罢 不亲近也好
he's the only one
也就是他
to bid you
就当
farewell.
最后的诀别吧
Write down anything
有什么要说的
you want to say.
可以记下来
Or you'll never
现在不说
have a chance later.
就真的没有机会说了
Thank you.
谢谢
Last time in Nanjing,
上次在南京见到你
you said you're ready
你说你要去
for navy training.
南洋远航训练
At that time,
我还在想
I was thinking
按道理应该
I should take you aboard myself.
我亲自送你登舰远航
I'm sorry
抱歉
to meet you here
今天我却以
in this way.
这样的方式跟你见面
They say
老师
you've joined the Communist Party.
他们说您加入了共产党
Is that true?
是真的吗
You've fought with the former PM
您曾陪伴先总理
for many times.
南征北战
You're a warrior and hero.
是战士 也是功臣
I really don't
学生实在不理解
understand your choice.
您的选择
Everyone has an ideal,
每个人都有理想
which will
而且理想
affect judgements
会决定他的判断
and the direction of progress.
和努力的方向
That's how
我的理想
I was influenced.
就决定了我的方向
What's your ideal?
那您的理想是什么
When you're 12,
你还记得吗
You boarded the
你十二岁那年
Ship Yongfeng with me,
随我登上永丰舰
telling me to
那时候你要
defend our country no matter what.
穷天地保家国
Actually,
那是你少年时的理想
it's also my dream when I was in the navy.
也是我当海军时的理想
Until today,
中华崛起
I'm still committed to
国泰民安
dedicating everything
到今天
to the peace and security of the country.
我的理想依然如此
In your opinion,
您是觉得
it can't be separated
只有加入共产党
from the Communist Party.
才能实现理想
So you become
所以您和他们
a member of them.
站在了一起
5 years ago,
五年前
the northeastern area fell.
东三省沦亡
And now,
现如今
the north China is in a precarious situation.
华北五省朝不保夕
People may say
有人说
we compromise to avoid wars.
妥协是为了不陷入战争
But what is war?
什么是战争
It often
往往在你
breaks out
无力于战争的时候
when you're powerless.
战争就爆发
We lost Taiwan
从甲午海战痛失台湾
in the First Sino-Japanese War.
一直到今天
There's no one but knows
能战者方能止战
that people who can fight can stop war.
他们不懂这个道理吗
Compromise can never
以地事秦
finally solve problems,
犹抱薪救火
but only aggravate contradictions.
薪不尽火不灭
At present,
大敌当前
our country is in danger.
国家危难
Regardless of party or origin,
不谈党派 不论出身
we should all fight together.
都应该奋起抗争
The Chinese nation
我中国
has a history of over 5,000 years.
五千年历史之民族
How could it
岂能亡于
be defeated by a tiny country?
区区三岛倭奴之手
Mr. Deng,
老师
I've asked you
在南京的时候
in Nanjing...
我曾问过你
Resisting aggression is not politics.
抗日不是政治
The northeast China has fallen.
东北沦陷
The north China is endangered.
华北事变
We will finally be at war
我们终有一天
with those Japanese invaders.
会和日寇一战
If we have to fight one day,
如果真的到了那一天
will you return to the battlefield?
您会重回战场吗
Sure.
会
I will.
一定会
Now I understand
现在我终于明白了
that you never stop fighting.
您从未离开过战场